Guide to the John Armstrong Chaloner papers, 1862-1935
David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library
John Armstrong Chaloner papers 1862-1935
David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library
Chaloner, John Armstrong, 1862-1935.
14 linear feet Extent: Approx. 6,500 Items
Great-grandson of John Jacob Astor; from Cobham (Albemarle County), Virginia. Business and personal correspondence, legal briefs, literary manuscripts, and miscellaneous papers. The letters, about half of the collection, are concerned with John Chaloner's attempts to have himself declared sane after a four-year involuntary internment in Bloomingdale Asylum at White Plains, N.Y. Letters also concern the circulation of some of his poetry; and congratulations to Chaloner on obtaining a favorable verdict regarding his sanity in the U.S. Supreme Court. The literary manuscripts are generally confined to treatises on the lunacy laws of various states. Other letters refer to the encouragment of film industry in rural areas. Included also are photographs; cancelled checks; telegrams; invitations and clippings, the latter largely confined to the career of his divorced wife, the novelist Amélie Rives. Among the correspondents are Philip Alexander Bruce, Richard Evelyn Byrd, J. H. Choate, Walter Duranty, A. C. Gordon, Joseph Jastrow, Claude Kitchin, Lee Slater Overman, and W. L. Phelps.
RL.00223
Language: Material in English
Administrative Information
Access Restrictions
Collection is open for research.
Researchers must register and agree to copyright and privacy laws before using this collection.
All or portions of this collection may be housed off-site in Duke University's Library Service Center. The library may require up to 48 hours to retrieve these materials for research use.
Please contact Research Services staff before visiting the David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library to use this collection.
Provenance
The John Armstrong Chaloner Papers were acquired by the David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library from 1936-1954.
Collection Overview
Collection contains business and personal correspondence, legal briefs, literary manuscripts, and miscellaneous papers belonging to John A. Chaloner, eccentric millionaire and great-grandson of John Jacob Astor. The letters, about half of the collection, are concerned with Chaloner's attempts to have himself declared sane after involuntary internment in Bloomingdale Asylum at White Plains, N.Y. by his family because of his excessive interest in spiritualism. He escaped from the asylum after four years. The letters contain mentions of his efforts to regain possession of his estate; verdicts from pyschologists concerning his mental condition; content on the fostering of motion pictures for rural areas; the circulation of some of his poems on European politics prior to 1914; and congratulations to Chaloner on obtaining a favorable verdict regarding his sanity in the U.S. Supreme Court.
The literary manuscripts are generally confined to treatises on the lunacy laws of various states. The briefs and legal notes are concerned with trials and appeals against the state of New York, and against the Washington Post for slander. Other materials in the collection include cancelled checks; telegrams; photographs; invitations and clippings, the latter chiefly related to the career of his divorced wife, novelist Amélie Rives, who later married Prince Pierre Troubetzkoy, and to the comment caused by the popular phrase coined by Chaloner: "Who's looney now?" Among the correspondents are Philip Alexander Bruce, Richard Evelyn Byrd, J. H. Choate, Walter Duranty, A. C. Gordon, Joseph Jastrow, Claude Kitchin, Lee Slater Overman, and W. L. Phelps.
Subject Headings
These are searchable subject entries for this collection. Performing a search on these subjects in the Duke University Libraries online catalog will bring up other related research materials.
Chaloner, John Armstrong, 1862-1935; Bruce, Philip Alexander, 1863-1945; Byrd, Richard Evelyn, 1888-1957; Choate, Joseph Hodges, 1832-1917; Duranty, Walter, 1884-1957; Gordon, Armistead C. (Armistead Churchill), 1855-1931.; Jastrow, Joseph, 1863-1944; Kitchin, Claude, 1869-1923; Overman, Lee S. (Lee Slater), 1854-1930; Phelps, William Lyon, 1865-1943; Rives, Amélie, 1863-1945; Insanity (Law)--United States; Mentally ill -- Commitment and detention -- United States; Motion picture industry -- United States; Trials (Malpractice)--New York (State)--New York; Photographs
Related Material
United States Supreme and N.Y. Circuit Court Chaloner trial records [three electronic resources]
Duke University Libraries
John Armstrong Chaloner Papers [147 items]
Albert and Shirley Small Special Collections Library, University of Virginia
Contents of Collection
- John Armstrong Chaloner Papers, 1862-1935, (28 boxes)
  - Letters, 1782-1893, VIII-E (Box 1)
  - Letters, 1894-1900, VIII-E (Box 2)
  - Letters, 1901-1903, May, VIII-E (Box 3)
  - Letters, 1903, June-1904, VIII-E (Box 4)
  - Letters, 1905-1906, VIII-E (Box 5)
  - Letters, 1907-1909, VIII-E (Box 6)
  - Letters, 1910-1913, VIII-E (Box 7)
  - Letters, 1914-1917, VIII-E (Box 8)
  - Letters, 1918-1922, VIII-E (Box 9)
  - Letters, 1923-1932, VIII-E (Box 10)
  - Letters, undated (Box 11)
  - Bills, receipts, and miscellaneous (Box 11)
  - Letters, undated (Box 12)
  - Legal papers (Box 13)
  - Legal papers, 1891-1919 and undated (Box 14-15)
  - Legal papers, 1893-1909 (Box 16)
  - Legal papers, 1911-1917 (Box 17)
  - Legal papers, 1918-1925 (Box 18)
  - Literary, 1891-1904 (Box 19)
  - Literary, 1905-1911 (Box 20)
  - Literary, 1912-1915 (Box 21)
  - Literary, 1916-1921 (Box 22)
  - Literary, 1922-1933 and undated (Box 23)
  - Literary, undated (Box 24)
  - Printed material, 1897-1917 (Box 25)
  - Printed material, 1918-1931 (Box 26)
  - Clippings (Box 27-28)
  - Photographs (Box 28)
  - Bound volumes (Box 28)
  - Bound manuscript volume (Volume L:519)